Guide to the Daniel Cassidy Papers AIA.049
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Daniel Cassidy Papers
Bulk, 2000-2008
1844-2008
AIA.049
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
4.0 linear feet in 3 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, and 1 half manuscript box.
Daniel Cassidy (1943-2008), Irish-American writer, singer, filmmaker, and professor. Beginning his career as a musician and screenwriter, Cassidy later turned his interests towards research and academia, focusing on storytelling, newspaper writing, and broadcast history. A prolific writer, Cassidy’s works include numerous newspaper and journal articles, as well as the book How the Irish Invented Slang: The Secret Language of the Crossroads. Materials in this collection include notes, manuscript drafts, annotated newspapers, play scripts, census documents, and annotated research files. The material primarily documents Cassidy’s research interests and film work, with smaller portions concerning his personal life and his time with both the New College of California and the Crossroads Irish American Festival.
Cassidy, Daniel
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Biographical Note
Daniel Cassidy (1943-2008), an Irish-American writer, singer, filmmaker, and professor, was born in Brooklyn in 1943. He attended the the New York Military Academy on a musical scholarship, and studied English Literature and Creative Writing at Cornell University. His first job was at the New York Times, which he left to pursue screenwriting full time. From the late 1960s through the 1980s, Cassidy performed as a musician, but gradually transitioned into composing his own music. He performed at, among other places, Carnegie Hall, the LA Civic Auditorium, and on the Tonight Show. In addition to his musical work, Cassidy was also a prolific screenwriter--he sold film scripts and treatments, and worked in both film development and television production. His 1996 documentary, Civil Rights and Civil Wrongs, about the Troubles in Northern Ireland, was nominated for an Emmy Award, and his film Uncensored Voices aired on PBS.
In the 1990s, Cassidy’s interests turned toward research and academia. Cassidy was a professor at New College of California, in the Media & Film Studies Department, where he taught storytelling, newspaper writing, and broadcast history classes. In 1995, he founded the Irish Studies Program (An Leann Eireannach) at New College. Cassidy was co-director of the program, one of the first in the country, until the college closed in 2008. Additionally, Cassidy was co-founder of the Crossroads Irish American Festival in San Francisco, and served as director of the festival until his death.
Cassidy was a prolific contributor to newspapers and journals. His book, How the Irish Invented Slang: The Secret Language of the Crossroads, was published in 2007. The book, which looked at the influence of Irish phrases on slang that developed in America in the 1800s, won the 2007 American Book Award for nonfiction. The book was met with much praise from within the Irish-American community, but was criticized by linguists for lacking evidence to support the book’s claims. Cassidy’s other research interest was African-American and Irish intermarriage in New York City in the 1800s, although he did not develop this enough before his death to publish any scholarly work on the topic. Cassidy died on October 11, 2008.
Scope and Content Note
This collection comprises material primarily relating to the research interests and film work of Daniel Cassidy, with smaller portions of the collection dealing with his personal papers as well as his time with both New College of California and the Crossroads Irish American Festival. Materials include awards, correspondence, newspapers, annotated secondary source materials, original writings, and play scripts.
Separated Materials
Duplicate copies of unnanotated newspapers and journals were removed from the collection. Additionally, photocopied duplicates of annotated play scripts were also removed. An unannotated photocopy of the full text of Criminal Slang: The Vernacular of the Underworld Lingo by Vincent Monteleone was removed from the collection; a copy of the book is available in Bobst. Personal material was removed from the collection and returned to the family.
Arrangement
The Daniel Cassidy Papers are arranged in four series:
Series I. Research and Publications
Series II. Personal Papers
Series III. Film
Series IV. Media
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Provenance is unknown. The accession number associated with this collection is 2010.070.
New College of California.; Clippings (information artifacts); Documentary films.; Hunger strikes |z Northern Ireland.; Immigrants |z United States; Interracial marriage |z United States |x History |y 19th century.; Ireland |x Emigration and immigration.; Irish Americans; Irish Americans |v Newspapers.; Irish Americans |z California.; Irish Americans |z New York (State); Irish Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs.; Irish language |x History; Irish language |x Influence on English.; Jazz |x History; Manhattan (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions.; Newspapers.; Research notes.; Screenplays.; Scripts (documents).; Vaudeville.
- Series I: Research & Publications, 1986-2008
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I: Research & Publications consists of material relating to the two main focuses of Cassidy’s research: tracing the Irish language in America and African-American/Irish intermarriage in New York City in the 1800s (what Cassidy called “Black Irish”). It includes Cassidy’s typed notes and draft manuscripts, annotated historical newspaper clippings and play scripts, census documents, and extensive annotated secondary source material, as well as a large collection of notebooks containing Cassidy’s own research notes, which deal with both of these research interests as well as his New College classes. Although there is some overlap between Cassidy's two areas of focus, the majority of his annotations on the secondary source material, newspapers, and plays have to do with his research on the Irish language and American slang. Cassidy's annotations on on the census documents focus on African-American/Irish intermarriage.
  - How the Irish Invented Slang Research, Drafts, and Notes, 2000-2008 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - How the Irish Invented Slang Drafts, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - How the Irish Invented Slang Drafts, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Slanguage Column Drafts, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Jazz: Historical Newspapaper Clippings, Part 1 of 2, [2000s] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Jazz: Historical Newspaper Clippings, Part 2 of 2, [2000s] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Nosey Blivens Lines 'Em Out column, [2000s] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Scoop Gleeson Columns, [2000s] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Slang: Historical Newspaper Clippings, [2000s] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Irish Travellers/Shelta Research, [2000s] (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Black Irish: Drafts and Notes, Part 1 of 2, [1990s] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Black Irish: Drafts and Notes, Part 2 of 2, [1990s] (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 8th Ward, 1860 - Irish-African Inter-Marriages, [1990s] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1850 U.S. Federal Census Records, [1990s] (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1860 U.S. Federal Census Records, [1990s] (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1870 U.S. Federal Census Records, [1990s] (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1880 U.S. Federal Census Records, [1990s] (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1920 U.S. Federal Census Records, [1990s] (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Annotated Secondary Sources, A-B, [2000s] (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Annotated Secondary Sources, C-D, [2000s] (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Annotated Secondary Sources, E, [2000s] (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Annotated Secondary Sources, F, [2000s] (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Annotated Secondary Sources, G-J, [2000s] (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Annotated Secondary Sources, K, [2000s] (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Annotated Secondary Sources, L, [2000s] (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Annotated Secondary Sources, M, Part 1 of 2, [2000s] (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Annotated Secondary Sources, M, Part 2 of 2, [2000s] (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Peter Tamony: Word Man of San Francisco's Mission/McLain, Marjorie, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Annotated Secondary Sources, N-O, [2000s] (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Annotated Secondary Sources, T-Z, [2000s] (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - The Hidden Ireland/Corkery, Daniel, [2000s] (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Annotated Secondary Sources, Unknown Attribution, [2000s] (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Radio Free Erin: How the Irish Became White Debate/Ignatiev & Quinn, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Anna Christie: A Play in Four Acts/O'Neill, Eugene, [2000s] (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Cordelia's Aspirations/Harrington, Edward, Part 1 of 2, [2000s] (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Cordelia's Aspirations/Harrington, Edward, Part 2 of 2, [2000s] (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - An t-Impire Mac Seoin ( The Emperor Jones)/O'Neill, Eugene, [2000s] (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The Mulligan Guard Ball/Harrington, Edward, [2000s] (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Mulligan Guard Nominee/Harrington, Edward, Annotated copy 1, Part 1 of 2, [2000s] (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The Mulligan Guard Nominee/Harrington, Edward, Annotated copy 1, Part 2 of 2, [2000s] (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - The Mulligan Guard Nominee/Harrington, Edward, Annotated copy 2, Part 1 of 2, [2000s] (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The Mulligan Guard Nominee/Harrington, Edward, Annotated copy 2, Part 2 of 2, [2000s] (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - The Mulligan Guard Nominee/Harrington, Edward, Annotated copy 3, [2000s] (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Mulligan's Silver Wedding/Harrington, Edward, Annotated copy 1, [2000s] (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Mulligan's Silver Wedding/Harrington, Edward, Annotated copy 2, Part 1 of 2, [2000s] (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Mulligan's Silver Wedding/Harrington, Edward, Annotated copy 2, Part 2 of 2, [2000s] (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Reilly and the Four Hundred/Harrington, Edward, [2000s] (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Clippings Authored by Cassidy, 1997-2008 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Notebook 1, 2001-2008 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Notebook 2, 2002-2008 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Notebook 3, 2004-2008 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Notebook 4, 2004-2008 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Notebook 5, 2004-2008 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Notebook 6, 2003-2008 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Notebook 7, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Notebook 8, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Notebook 9, ca. 2000 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Notebook 10, 2005-2008 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Notebook 11, 1997-2008 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Notebook 12, 2005-2008 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Notebook 13, ca. 2000 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Notebook 14, ca. 2000 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Notebook 15, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Notebook 16, ca. 2000 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Notebook 17, ca. 2000 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Notebook 18, 2003-2008 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Notebook 19, 2001-2008 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Notebook 20, 2001-2008 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Notebook 21, ca. 2000 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Notebook 22, 2001-2008 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Notebook 23, 2004-2008 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Series II: Personal Papers, 1871-2008
  Series II: Personal Papers is relatively brief, and mostly contains awards, correspondence and newspaper clippings relating to Cassidy’s life and work, as well as his research into his personal family history. The correspondence that was provided with the collection is very sporadic, and consists of emails written and printed out by Cassidy, and notes from friends and colleagues regarding his illness. The newspaper clippings differ from those in Series I, as these are clippings about, not authored by, Cassidy. The most significant portion of material in this series relates to Cassidy’s work on tracing his own family’s genealogy.
  - Personal Email/Correspondence, 2004-2008 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Family Genealogy, 1871-2008 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Awards/Certificates, 2000-2008 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - New College of California/Crossroads Irish-American Festival, 2000-2007 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Clippings About Cassidy, 1998-2007 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Series III: Film, 1987-1997
  Series III: Film includes Cassidy’s scripts, screenplays, and film treatments. It includes many final versions of these, as well as draft manuscripts, research notes, and correspondence relating to his film work.
  - Film Correspondence, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Film Research Notes and Clippings, [1990s] (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Court Files, Extradition of Terence Damien Kirby, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - The Island Journal, 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Oral History Transcripts, Part 1 of 2, [1990s] (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Oral History Transcripts, Part 2 of 2, [1990s] (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Oral History Recording: Kevin, Day 3, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Untitled Manuscripts, [1990s] (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Untitled Script Drafts, [1990s] (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - The Buffalo Road script, ca. 1990 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - The Neighbor That Said 'No!' script, ca. 1990 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Ozark One screenplay, copy 1, ca. 1990 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Ozark One screenplay, copy 2, ca. 1990 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - South of Market script, ca. 1990 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - This Dance Can Kill script, ca. 1990 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - The Volunteer Film Treatment, Drafts and Notes, Part 1 of 2, 1993-1995 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - The Volunteer Film Treatment, Drafts and Notes, Part 2 of 2, 1993-1995 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - The Volunteer Film Treatment, ca. 1995 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Series IV: Media, 1994-2002
  Series, IV: Media, contains a collection of slides, cassette tapes, CDs, Hi8 tapes, and floppy discs, much of which could not be accessed. The CD contains photos from his book tour; and, from the labels, most of the material on the floppy discs consists of research notes and drafts, and the Hi8 tapes contain taped lectures.
  - Slides, 286 8th Avenue, NY NY, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Research Notes, Floppy Discs, 1996-2002 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Floppy Discs, Film, [1990s] (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Hi8 Tapes, 1994-2000 (Box 5, Folder 7)